Guide to the Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection ARC.202
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection
circa 1850 to 2010
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.202
12.6 Linear Feet in 23 manuscript boxes, one oversize box, one extra oversize box, and one flat file drawer.
The Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection contains approximately 7000 items dating from the mid 19th century to the beginning of the 21st.
Oversize XOS Box
Oversize Flat File; Drawer 3
Oversize OS Box
Box 12
Box 8
Box 7
Box 6
Box 5
Box 10
Box 14
Box 13
Box 1
Box 2
Box 3
Box 4
Box OS-38
Oversize OS-36
Box OS-41
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection contains approximately 7000 items dating from the mid 19th century to the beginning of the 21st. The collection provides comprehensive visual documentation of the borough of Brooklyn, N.Y., with images of neighborhoods, homes, buildings, businesses, parks, the waterfront, and infrastructure. Subjects of interest include aerial views of Brooklyn, major local banks, armories, bridges, churches, civic groups, libraries, museums, schools, parks, railroads, subway stations, and city and government agencies such as prisons, fire and police departments, and post offices. Over 30 Brooklyn neighborhoods are documented, including Brownstone Brooklyn, Williamsburg, Greenpoint, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Bushwick, Crown Heights, Brownsville, Canarsie, Flatlands, Sheepshead Bay, Gravesend, Coney Island, Bay Ridge, Sunset Park, Borough Park, and Flatbush. In addition to images of the Brooklyn Navy Yard (formally known as the New York Naval Shipyard), the collection also contains photographs of Brooklyn docks, harbors, and ferries.
The collection is divided into three groups. Series 1 consists of photographs numbered V1973.5 and accounts for the majority of the collection. Series 2 contains illustrations numbered V1973.6. Series 3, labeled "prints by subject," is unnumbered. The three groups are arranged alphabetically by subject, and subject indexes for each group are available in the library. Folder level description is available for Series 3 in this finding aid, while item-level description is available for Series 1 (V1973.5) and Series 2 (V1973.6) in the library's image database, PastPerfect. Users can search the PastPerfect database by neighborhood, street, business, or agency name, as well as by subject terms.
Other Finding Aids
Item-level description and digital versions of images from the groups V1973.5 (Series 1) and V1973.6 (Series 2) are available for searching via the image database in the library.
A full index of subjects in groups V1973.5, V1973.6, and "prints by subject" are available in paper form in library.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was formalized into a collection in 1973, but material was collected throughout the 20th century and into the 21st from various news agencies, magazines, journals, and other print publications.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Aerial photographs; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dwellings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Sea Gate (New York, N.Y.); Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park South (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Illustrations (layout features); Gerritsen Beach (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Flatlands (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Cobble Hill (New York, N.Y.); Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bath Beach (New York, N.Y.); Dyker Heights (New York, N.Y.); Panoramas; Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan Beach (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Gowanus (New York, N.Y.); Brighton Beach (New York, N.Y.); Banks and banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Armories |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); New Lots (New York, N.Y.); Civic improvement |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Libraries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Bridges |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Church buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Parks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Railroads |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Prisons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subway stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fire departments |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Post office buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc. |v Pictorial works; Black-and-white prints (prints on paper); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Exterior views; Studio portraits; Interior views; Cemeteries |z United States; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.) |v Pictorial works; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Fire fighters |z New York (State) |z New York; New York Naval Shipyard
- Series I: Photographs
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series has been fully digitized, and item-level description is available onsite in the library's image database PastPerfect. Users can search the database by neighborhood, street, business, or agency name, as well as by subject terms.
- Series II: Illustrations (Box 26, Box 27)
- Series III: Prints by Subject
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject, and is open for research without restrictions. This series has not been digitized.
  - American Revolution (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Animals (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Architecture (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Armories (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Army - People (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Artwork (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Asian Americans (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Aviation - Airmail planes (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Aviation - Airplanes (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Aviation - Airports (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Aviation - Dirigibles (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Aviation - People (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Bay Ridge (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Bedford Stuyvesant (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Bensonhurst (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Bergen Beach (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Boerum Hill (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Bridges (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Brooklyn - General (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Brooklyn Dodgers - Ebbets Field (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Brooklyn Eagle Statue (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1750-1850 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1851-1865 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1865-1900 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1900-1920 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1920-1940 (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1940-1960 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Brooklyn Heights - 1980-2000 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Brooklyn Heights - Church of Holy Trinity (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Dinners and Fundraisers (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Exteriors (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Library #1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Library #2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Openings (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Renovation (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Special Events (1900-2000) (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Staff #1 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society - Staff #2 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Brooklyn Navy Yard (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Buildings, Houses - Dutch Homesteads (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Buildings, Houses - Identified (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Buildings, Houses - Unidentified (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Business and Commerce - Advertisements (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Business and Commerce - Bars and Restaurants (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Business and Commerce - Business (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Business and Commerce - Commerce (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Business and Commerce - Factories/ Industrial (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Business and Commerce - Labor Movements (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Business and Commerce - Ladder Companies (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Business and Commerce - Merchants and Vendors (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Business and Commerce - Mills (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Business and Commerce - Women at work (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - California (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Canarsie (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Cemeteries (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Christmas (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Churches - Buildings (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Churches - Congregants (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Churches - Plymouth Church (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Civic Organizations - #1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Civic Organizations - #2 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Civic Organizations - Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce - Women (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Civic Organizations - Women (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Clubs and Associations #1 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Clubs and Associations #2 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Clubs and Associations #3 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Clubs and Associations #4 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Cobble Hill (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Coney Island - 1800s (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Coney Island - 1900-1950 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Coney Island - 1950-1970 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Coney Island - 1970-1980 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Coney Island - 1981-1990 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Coney Island -2010-2020 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Connecticut (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Decorative Arts (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Decorative Arts - Dutch (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1750-1850 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1850-1900 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1900-1920 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1920-1950 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1950-1980 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Downtown Brooklyn - 1980-2000 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Dumbo (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Engineering and Construction (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Farm Life (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Fire Department (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Fire Destruction (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Flatbush (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Flatlands (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Fort Greene (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Fort Hamilton (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Forts (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Gay Life (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Gowanus (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Gowanus - Gowanus Canal (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Gravesend (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Greenpoint (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Hospitals and Convalescence (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Interiors - By address (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Interiors - Unidentified (Box 19, Folder 17, Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Italian Americans (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Landscapes (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Latinx Americans (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Libraries (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Long Island (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Manhattan (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Maps (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Massachusetts (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Memorials, Markers, and Gravestones (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Midwood (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Military - Mounted Photos, Undated #1 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Military - Mounted Photos, Undated #2 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Military - Mounted Photos, Undated #3 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Mill Basin (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Motion Pictures (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Museums (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Museums - Brooklyn Botanical Garden (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Musicians, Conductors, Music groups (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Navy (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - New Jersey (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - New Utrecht (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - New York State (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - New York State - Historic America Building Survey 1937 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Parades (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Park Slope (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Parks (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Prisons (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Prospect Park (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Prospect Park - Grand Army Plaza (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Prospect Park - Plans and Drawings (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Prospect Park - Zoo (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Prospect-Lefferts Gardens (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Queens (Box 21, Folder 1, Box 25)
  - Rallies (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Red Hook (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Religion (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Religion - Judaism (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Rhode Island (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Russian Americans (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Schools (Box 21, Folder 8, Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Scotland (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Sheepshead Bay (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Shipping Industry (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Ships (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Spanish-American War - Cabinet Cards #1 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Spanish-American War - Cabinet Cards #2 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Spanish-American War - Camp Scenes (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Spanish-American War - Mounted Photos (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Spanish-American War - People (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Spanish-American War - Troop C (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Sports and Recreation - Acting and Theater (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Sports and Recreation - Athletics (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Sports and Recreation - Children (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Sports and Recreation - Gaming and Horseracing (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Sports and Recreation - Hunting (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Sports and Recreation - Oversize (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Staten Island (Box 22, Folder 8, Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Street Scenes and Buildings (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Sunset Park (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Television (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Transportation - Buses (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Transportation - Cars and Bicycles (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Transportation - Commuters (NY transit strike 1980) (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Transportation - Elevated Trains (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Transportation - Elevated Trains, Queens (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Transportation - Ferryboats (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Transportation - History (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Transportation - Horses (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Transportation - LIRR (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Transportation - Railroads (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Transportation - Stations (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Transportation - Subways (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Virginia (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Washington Centennial (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Waterfronts (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Weeksville (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - West Indian Americans (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Williamsburg (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - World War I (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - World War II (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - World's Fair 1939 (Box 23, Folder 16)